(light music)
(train sounding)
- [Narrator] Nearly everyone
in prison says he's innocent.
This is the story of one man
whose claim might actually be true.
- It's like a bad dream.
I wake up everyday
wondering what happened.
Why'd this happen to me?
I didn't break the law,
I didn't commit no crime.
My name's Clarence Elkins.
I was falsely accused
and wrongly convicted
for something I had nothin' to do with.
- [Narrator] The story of Clarence Elkins
begins just outside of Akron, Ohio,
in the small town of Barberton.
- My mom, she had dropped
me off and she said
that I was gonna be stayin' the
night at my grandma's house.
- Brooke was my mom's world,
'cause she had never had a
granddaughter, just grandsons.
And so that was kind of her favorite
because that was her little granddaughter.
- She was funny, she used to like...
(giggling)
I don't know how to tell
'em about the teeth thing.
Whenever you were sitting
down being serious,
she would always take her false teeth
and stick 'em out of her mouth,
so that was really funny.
(ominous music)
I heard a bunch of screaming,
so I ran to the kitchen
and I seen the guy lookin'
over top of my grandma,
like he had something in his hand.
He was yelling at her,
and I got really scared
and I ran back to my grandma's bedroom.
And I think he may have heard me
and came into the bedroom and hurt me.
- [April] She was beaten, raped,
strangled, sodomized, left for dead.
- The next morning, I woke
up and I shook my grandma,
and she wouldn't wake up,
so I kept on shaking her.
And I kept on screaming, Get up, get up!
And she wouldn't get up.
So I was looking for
the phone and I called
one of my grandma's friends,
June, no one answered.
(answering machine beeping)
I knocked on her door and I
asked her to take me home,
that my grandma was dead
and that someone killed her.
She took me and her three
daughters to my house.
- And then I woke up to
tremendous pounding on the front,
backdoor, and the side
windows of my house.
And so I opened the backdoor
and there stood Brooke
covered in blood in my mom's nightgown.
- They were asking, Who did
this, do you know who did this?
I said it looked like my Uncle Clarence.
He sounded like Uncle Clarence
and he was about the same height.
- And it was really, really
hard to me to believe
that he would do somethin' like that,
but I had to believer her.
She was there, she's the
one tellin' me all this.
- And then everyone was
freakin' out, sayin',
Oh my god, Clarence did it, oh my god.
- I was just so mad at him,
that he could do that to
my mom, let alone Brooke.
I just couldn't understand
why he would do that.
- [Narrator] Later that morning,
sheriff's deputies descend
upon Clarence's home.
- And I remember Clarence
going out the back door
and I seen him cross the window
and he kind of had his hands
up like what's goin' on?
- They were telling me to
put my hands in the air
and turn around, walk slowly backwards,
which I didn't because I didn't understand
what they were doing or what
they were at my home for.
- And then I seen two or
three police officers running
down the hill of our backyard
in helmets and vests and guns.
And of course I'm, what
the heck is goin' on here?
- [Narrator] Deputies
tell Melinda her mother
has been murdered and
Clarence is under arrest.
- I screamed, I ran in the house
and I called my grandmother,
because I just couldn't believe
what they were telling me.
My uncle was on the phone and he said,
Yes, she's dead and Brooke is
saying that it was Clarence.
- And so I went to the police station.
They tried to put words in my mouth
saying why I did this and why I done that,
and I just could not answer
one question they had.
My reaction to my niece when I first out
that she allegedly stated
that I had did this,
I was like my god, what
a terrible mistake.
I know this isn't coming from her.
This child is like one of my own children.
It's been a nightmare every since.
(light music)
Hearing them say guilty was devastating.
This wasn't happening to me,
this don't happen to people
like me that doesn't break
the law, is not a criminal.
- And it was the most excruciating feeling
when he looked at me...
And...
I looked at him and he put
his head down on the table.
I thought I was gonna die,
I couldn't believe it.
And they stood him up and they removed him
from the courtroom and I
told him that I loved him
and he looked back at me
and he said, I love you.
And I think there was a picture of that,
what I was feeling, because
I just couldn't believe it,
absolutely couldn't believe it.
I had to sell our home,
I had to find somewhere to
move, I had lost my job.
It was me and my sons,
period, that was it.
I had not a lot of support.
Clarence's family was devastated.
I couldn't go to my family.
So I had to concentrate on
getting myself together first.
And I did that, and then after that,
I decided, first of all,
Clarence needs new attorneys
and we need a private investigator.
Clarence is not guilty and I
was gonna somehow prove that.
♪ It's not my home ♪
♪ But here I am ♪
♪ Stealin' all your wishes ♪
♪ Better grab them while you can ♪
♪ I've been wrong ♪
Hi, Mom.
I love you and I miss you.
I made a vow to her that
I would find the truth,
find who did this to her,
if it took me forever.
Bye, Grandma.
♪ Countin' stars, there
must be a million ♪
♪ I could see them through the bars ♪
♪ I'm alone ♪
♪ But it's all right ♪
♪ I've got a dream to make it right ♪
♪ Healin' on light ♪
- So she walked up to my door
and my husband answered it.
She ask if she could come in.
- She first turned away from
me when I come to the door,
and then immediately turned back to me
and hugged me and cried.
And I thought, I've broken the ice now.
Now we can talk.
- I was glad that you came
over and tried talkin' to me.
I really, I don't know what I was thinkin'
at that point in time, but
I know that I had missed her
and I loved her and I wanted
to see if her and my nephews
were all right, so I chose
to talk to her that day.
And I'm glad I did.
Like I said, I've known Clarence
since I was eight years old.
So at the same time, when
I believed he was guilty,
there was still a doubt in my mind
that maybe he did not commit this crime.
This is Brooke's first grade picture.
I told my sister, whatever
you need, I'll do, interviews,
whatever we need to do to try
and get to the bottom of this.
(traffic passing)
- When a person accepts Christ the Savior,
they become born again,
the salvation takes place.
That they're saved, they're Christian.
When that happens, the
Holy Spirit's in them
and he starts guiding you to all truth.
- I just wanted to be in her life again.
I'm her aunt and I loved her.
And I wanted to be there for my sister.
I know that she was...
devastated by all of this, as we all have.
(light music)
So what happened was Brooke
wanted to come and visit.
- I always hung out with
my cousins in the garage
because they're really cool
people you could hangout with.
- And my son, Brandon,
had this photo gallery
of his dad out in the garage.
- And I seen Uncle
Clarence in a family photo
with all his brothers and I
noticed that he had blue eyes.
And later, I told Aunt
Mindy that the person
that killed mamaw didn't have
blue eyes, they had brown.
Sometimes I feel guilty because
it was my testimony
that put him in prison,
but they always tell me
that it's not my fault,
it's the police department's
fault and the prosecutors.
- Victim misidentification, bottom line.
- This is my brother's.
- I mean, you have to remember,
she was six years old.
She was beaten, raped, strangled,
sodomized, left for dead.
And she was just traumatized.
- I told them it wasn't sure who it was,
but then they're like,
Your Uncle Clarence did it.
So I was like, yeah, I guess.
- I'm Mark Godsey, I'm
a law professor here
at the University of
Cincinnati College of Law
and director of the
Ohio Innocence Project.
Our mission is to look at old cases
where the inmates have
steadfastly maintained
their innocence from
the beginning to the end
and see if there's some sort of evidence,
new evidence, that might be
able to shed light on it.
- The brother and the sister
don't really get along.
- The Innocence Projects use law students
to investigate the cases of
people who they're innocent
and look into DNA testing
and other technologies.
So it's a real hands on
experience for the students.
- They liked Bill for this
crime from the very start.
He has priors, assault,
hardcore drug convictions.
- My name is Michelle Berry.
I'm a third year student
here at UC Law School.
And the reason I came to UC Law School
actually was because of
the Ohio Innocence Project.
- The simple mission is to
get innocent people out of prison.
- One of the greatest
feelings in the world
is knowin' that you're helpin' someone
who really needs your help
and is actually innocent.
- We definitely get tons
and tons of letters.
Just last year I think we had about 500.
- You take everyone who's
written in and says,
I'm innocent, please help me.
The first thing that
happens if you determine
whether this is a case where DNA
could actually prove you innocent
and it the type of crime where
DNA would have been left.
75% of those cases, the answer's no.
- So there's a lot that's
wrong with the case,
there's not a whole lot
of exculpatory evidence.
- Some people see me
as a defense attorney.
I don't see myself as a
defense attorney at all.
I only go forward, and we only go forward,
we think the evidence
proves they're innocent.
- I first apologized
for calling him at home,
but he was like, Oh, no, no, that's okay.
- She's very compelling
when you listen to her
and we ended up having this
hour or two hour conversation
where she filled me in on everything,
and I just kept wanting
to hear more and more
'cause it sounded like such a good case,
a case where we had a real good chance
of havin' someone innocent here
that we could do justice with.
(light music)
The crucial, I think,
investigative part of the case
was when we had a two page list
of all the items taken
from the crime scene,
and most of those had never been tested.
And we had a limited amount of money,
we didn't have the money
to test everything,
so we had to make strategic decisions
on what was gonna be tested.
- We had a slam dunk case then and there.
Evidence that could only have
been left by the true attacker
and completely excluded Mr. Elkins.
- Before that, there's always some doubt.
Maybe you're helpin' someone
who's not really innocent,
but then when you get it
back and you feel vindicated,
you feel like you've done
something really good
and now it's just a
matter of going to court
or getting the prosecutor to
agree and get 'em out of there.
- So we went forward with
that and made a motion
that lead to a hearing in March of 2005.
We got up and we argued to the judge.
Judge, we know who the true killer is.
We don't know his name,
but here's his DNA profile
on the chalkboard, it's
not Clarence Elkins
and Clarence Elkins should be exonerated.
And I think on that evidence,
if you were to play Russian roulette
and drop yourself in any
courthouse in America,
you'd win about 99% of the time.
If you can believe it, we actually lost
that hearing in July of 2005.
The judge came down with the
decision denying our motion
and that Clarence had to spend
the rest of his life in prison.
(train horn sounding)
(light music)
- A new trial at the least was denied?
(doors slamming)
There's something wrong with this picture.
What doesn't these people understand?
These people are supposed to
be people that uphold the law.
That's not justice, that's
not what the people deserve,
that's not what I deserve.
That's not what my mother in
law and my niece deserves.
♪ Tell you what was wrong ♪
- I was totally devastated.
Sorry.
I just broke down, I cried and I sobbed
and I couldn't collect myself.
I just couldn't believe it.
What more do that want?
Do they want us to serve them
who did this on a silver platter to them?
Well, okay then, that's what we'll do.
- [Mark] For people who
are innocent in prison,
the police aren't gonna
investigate their cases,
because are far as the police
is concerned, they're guilty.
And so Melinda was really
the detective in this case
and she was going out in the town,
getting tips and following up on leads.
And we were all brainstorming
on who could have done this crime.
- And then at one point, we
had this list of suspects.
When the DNA testing
come around that time,
we really had to start thinkin',
well, which ones are we gonna have tested?
Which ones do we want
to try to get DNA from?
- I remember having several conversations
with her where she'd say,
I'm gonna go in and meet
this guy in a bar tonight
and I'm gonna walk out
with his beer better.
- And I concentrated on people that I knew
around the Barberton area
that had a colorful past
who might be capable
of something like this.
And I would interject
myself into their lives
and just follow them, and
the knew me well enough
as Judy's daughter and April's sister
that I could talk to them
and they wouldn't suspect
that I was getting their DNA on the sly.
And I would get a beer bottle or a glass,
and I had some of the
bartenders helping me.
It was pretty sickening to have to pretend
like you're talking to
these people as a friend
when you're actually thinking
is this the person that killed my mom?
Looking back on it now, if
they ever would have suspected,
then I just wonder what
could have happened to me.
But I was focused and I know
that I needed to do this
because there wasn't anyone
else to do that, so I did it.
I'm heading to Tonia Brasiel's house,
the front door, actually.
- Tonia Brasiel is the woman
who lived two doors down
and the morning that the crime occurred,
Brooke Sutton, the little girl,
woke up and ran two doors down for help.
- I knocked on her door and
I asked her to take me home,
that my grandma was dead
and that someone killed her.
- Tonia Brasiel answers the door,
instead of doing what you would expect,
which is call the police,
call an ambulance,
call her mom, she closes the door.
- She didn't let my niece in that morning.
She puts her in her
car and takes her home.
- And I ask her, I said, Why
did you not go check on my mom?
And she said that she was scared
someone was still in there
and that they would hurt
her and the children.
And I said, Well, did you call
911, did you call the police,
did you call anyone to get my mom help?
And she said no.
- I couldn't understand, I mean,
a child would come to my door
in the shape that Brooke was in,
she was very disheveled
and bloody and injured,
your first instinct would
be to take that child in
and protect her, and then call the police.
- She became, Tonia Brasiel,
the woman two doors down,
the key witness against Clarence Elkins,
in addition to the little girl,
because her testimony at trial was,
When the little girl knocked on my door,
she was screaming over
and over again that,
It was my Uncle Clarence,
it was my Uncle Clarence,
I'm positive it was my Uncle Clarence!
And so you actually had
an adult corroborating
and backing up this weak testimony
from a six year old girl.
- I just kept going
back to that and I kept,
why would somebody do that?
What would be the reason?
Is there something they
were trying to hide?
(light music)
I'd come across a newspaper article
that featured her name with Earl Mann,
who was her common law husband,
and that they were both being charged
for rape of three children.
- Specifically, Earl Mann was convicted
and Tonia Brasiel was convicted
for aiding and abetting him.
And these were anal rapes,
which matched what had
happened in this crime.
- And I thought, my god, the possibility
that he's a child rapist, there
was some kind of light bulb
that went off that said to me,
you need to look at this guy.
- And looking at the records,
which you could all see on the internet,
he got out of prison on June 2nd
and then was picked up again
for another crime on June 15th,
and the murders occurred and
the rapes occurred on June 7th.
So he was out of a window
for about 13 days there,
staying at that house where
his common law wife was.
So it all just fit and immediately
he becomes the top suspect.
- He had close proximity,
it's just second steps away
from my mom's front door.
I'm thinking that he had
quick access to my mom's house
and quick access back home
without being detected.
Knowing that he lived here
and what his background was,
I'm really thinking that he's the person
that murdered and raped my mom
and attacked and raped my niece.
- Also on the computer,
you can type in Earl Mann,
on the websites we go to,
and see where he's in prison
for raping these little girls.
And low and behold, he's in
prison with Clarence Elkins.
(background chattering)
(light music)
- My wife Melinda told me of this suspect
that she had in mind, and
there was several ways
I thought about retrieving DNA.
I didn't wanna point a finger
at somebody I wasn't sure of.
Once and for all, the opportunity arose.
He had smoked a cigarette,
sittin' there at the table,
so there was a single
cigarette butt in this ashtray.
And it was just the perfect time.
I had some tissue in my
pocket and I took the tissue,
reached into the ashtray with
the tissue without touching it
and wrapped it up, put it in plastic,
and mailed it out in a envelope.
- It was just a shock,
and everybody in my office
could hear me saying, Oh, thank god.
Oh my god, what?
- If we had a slam dunk case before,
we now have a 360 dunk from the foul line
that breaks the backboard, this was it.
- All's I could say was it
had to be divine intervention.
This person was put in my path,
so to speak, for a reason.
I thank the Lord everyday for it.
- We got the results back from Earl Mann,
showing that the true
killer was Earl Mann.
And having gone through
what we already went through
after we'd previously proven
that Clarence was innocent,
and we saw that there's nothing we can do
to change the mind of these prosecutors,
there's nothing we can do to
change the mind of the judge,
we decided we needed some help,
we needed to do something
unusual to turn the tide.
- [Narrator] Mark Godsey
decides to reach out
to the state's top law
enforcement official,
Attorney General Jim Petro.
- And when I had the
opportunity to hear the story
of Clarence Elkins, I
found it very compelling.
This looks like this guy
could really be innocent.
We have to do all that we can to assist
if in fact there's
evidence to suggest that.
- It wasn't a matter of one in hundred,
one in a thousand, one in a
million, one in two billion,
it was absolutely 100%
not Clarence Elkins.
- I'd asked my chief deputy
for criminal justice,
Jim Canepa, to please
communicate personally,
sit down and have a
discussion with the prosecutor
or with the prosecutor's chief deputy.
And we found it very
difficult to arrange that.
- I actually traveled to Akron
to meet with the county prosecutor,
tried to speak to her both
in person and by phone,
and for whatever reasons,
that wasn't accommodated.
- Maybe they thought that
we were sticking our nose in
where it didn't belong, but
that's really not the case.
We do have a good deal of
criminal investigative authority
when invited by local
law enforcement agencies.
And this is pretty compelling,
you really oughta be looking at this,
because no one wants to sit
back and let a guy sit in jail
when he might in fact really be innocent.
- The DNA evidence connecting Earl Mann
was very powerful originally and there was
a less than one in 4,000 chance
that it was someone else,
which is very, very powerful.
But as the prosecution
argued in their attempts
to protect Earl Mann and
avoid admitting a mistake
had been made with Clarence
Elkins, they said, well,
that's several hundred
men in the state of Ohio.
Of course, if you took those
several hundred men
and put them in a room,
some of them would be two year old babies
and some of them would be 98 year old men,
some of them would be African
American and different races.
And the number of these other men in Ohio
that had this DNA profile
who are convicted rapists,
child rapists, who live two doors down
from the crime scene would be zero.
- [Crowd] Free Clarence
now, free Clarence now!
Free Clarence now, free Clarence now!
Free Clarence now, free
Clarence now, free Clarence now!
- This is not about myself.
This is for my mother in law and my niece.
And for the public in general.
I think there's a lesson to be learned
for a lot of people in this situation.
Injustices can happen,
as they happened to me,
and I wouldn't ever want that
to happen to anyone else.
I want justice for everyone.
And the person that
committed this crime...
be held accountable.
(light music)
- I think the real question here is,
when you absolutely know
the person is innocent,
what can you do to speed that process up?
The guy is innocent, what can we do
to get him out before Christmas?
- Well, right now we're getting ready
to go to the attorney
general's press conference,
so I think this would be
the best Christmas present
that any of us could ever ask for.
I'm feelin' it now, I'm just...
nervous.
- A few minutes before our
press conference starts,
we get a call from them
telling us that they've agreed,
that they're gonna be announcing it there
that Clarence is innocent
and he's gonna be released.
Jim Petro, the attorney
general, just came in
and announced that Summit County
is holding a press conference
at the same time as ours
and they're gonna announce that
they're dropping all charges
against Clarence and
his immediate release.
(Melinda sobbing)
Apparently what had
happened, we learned later,
is that they had started
interrogating Earl Mann
after they got the pubic hair match.
And he had made several
incriminating statements.
They'd finally come around to the view
that Clarence was innocent.
- When we commenced to call you in today
to make another announcement,
we were announcing
the completion of scientific
testing by criminologists.
That information was provided yesterday
to the prosecutor's office,
and I guess, I'm not tryin'
to steal their announcement,
but they're making
a comparable announcement
in Akron at 11:00.
- Press release, Summit County prosecutor
moves to free man
convicted in slaying rape.
Summit County prosecutor
Sherri Bevan Walsh
today filed a motion to
clear Clarence Elkins,
who was convicted in 1999 of
the murder of his mother in law
and the rape of his six year old niece.
- Yeah, he's been exonerated,
they dropped all the charges
and he's getting out late this afternoon.
- If we can get the entry from the judge.
I was tryin' to figure out a way
to get a phone call into
Clarence, because at that point,
he was being protected
in protective custody.
But I got right through
and I was really excited
that she was gonna be
able to talk to Clarence
and give him the news herself.
Okay, very good.
- [Man] Okay, well I need to run because--
- It's Nannette?
Hey, Clarence?
What are you doin', honey?
You okay?
You ready to come home?
Then get your stuff packed, honey,
'cause you're comin' home today.
- [Clarence] Well, God
bless all of you guys.
You guys are amazing.
- [Mark] You're amazing, Clarence.
- [Clarence] Oh my god,
I'm just so grateful.
- [Mark] Hey Clarence?
- [Clarence] What?
- Have you known that
this has been going on?
We've all been frantic
for the past 24 hours.
- [Clarence] I thought maybe
it was gonna go a little while
longer yet, but this is it.
(light music)
- Nobody's gonna be allowed
past this flagpole, please.
- Not past the flagpole.
- [Woman] Don't worry,
I won't get in the shot.
- [Man] Hey, Clarence!
- Thank God, thank God.
I'm very proud of everyone
that stepped forward
on my behalf for justice.
- [Woman] What are you gonna do?
- [Man] Pinch yourself?
- I don't know, one day at a time,
slow and easy, putting
my life back together.
Freedom!
- [Woman] How are you
gonna spend Christmas?
- [Clarence] With my family.
- [Man] What do you want for Christmas?
- I got what I wanted for Christmas,
my life back with my family.
♪ All the chains, they can rattle ♪
♪ Won't scare me away from you ♪
♪ And all the vainest attempts ♪
♪ Just leave snide hesitation words ♪
- This is Uncle Woody's, it's a bar
right across the street
from the law school
where it's the local watering
hole for the law students.
They come to celebrate things,
so here today celebrating
the Clarence Elkins case.
This is the first time
we've gotten together since he got out.
- It's an inspiration that I know
that I'm gonna carry with
me throughout my career.
Knowing that I'm picking up these skills
and gaining this knowledge
and I'm able to use that
to help people who
can't do it on their own
and have no other resort,
I just know that's what I'm meant to do.
- Do I think the justice
system is this beautiful thing
that we learn about in sixth
grade social studies class?
Absolutely not, but do
I believe in justice?
Absolutely.
- [Crowd] Free Clarence
now, free Clarence now!
- The criminal justice
system isn't perfect,
but if you fight hard enough
and you have a lot of people on your side,
you can eventually win.
- All right guys, let's have
a toast to all the hard work
that all of you guys have done,
not only in the Elkins case,
but all the other cases.
A great result, and to Clarence.
- [All] To Clarence!
(cheering)
(light music)
♪ Gonna sit by my window ♪
♪ I'll just watch the leaves blow away ♪
- This here road, Irish
Road, is where I used to live
in Magnolia, Ohio, seven
and a half years ago.
♪ There's so much that you can take ♪
♪ Inside yourself before you break ♪
I had, oh, approximately four acres.
Used to hunt in all these woods here.
♪ There's no place for castaways ♪
♪ Like you and I to call home ♪
This just brings back a lot
of memories, being here.
We had a lot of good times
here and this was home.
This was home seven and a half years ago.
And it was all taken in an instant.
It's very difficult, very sad at times.
It's not like it used to be, but...
at the same time, I gotta move on.
And that's our goal, is to move on
and try to rebuild our lives.
- The really hard part for
me, I'll speak for myself,
I wasn't expecting
through all the happiness
and the sense of accomplishment,
through all of that,
I was not expecting this rock of...
sadness to come over me as it did...
for my mom.
I'm now starting that grieving
process that I never got
to do and it's really
hit me extremely hard.
My reaction has been
to go inside of myself,
because I've only had myself
to rely on, pretty much.
I've made it that way only
because I had to put up a wall.
And that wall has doubled for me.
I feel very disconnected from everyone.
- [Narrator] Shortly
after his exoneration,
Clarence and Melinda become estranged.
- The hardest part is my wife is Melinda,
who's been so amazing in her
efforts to get to the truth
and find out who did this.
So she is not finished at this time.
She's still in the
fight mode, so to speak.
So it's been very rough on us.
She's havin' a hard time
adjusting to me, I guess.
I don't know, I really don't know.
That's the hardest thing
I'm going through right
now and very painful.
It's not what I want at all.
That's about all I can
say right now about that.
- [Narrator] With nowhere else to go,
Clarence moves back to his parent's home.
- Yep, home for Christmas,
home for the New Years.
Start off the new year good.
Everything's changed.
(knocking)
And just tryin' to rebuild my life.
That's a major, major task in itself.
It's great to be home.
I'm just hoping for a good ending.
That me and my wife
can be husband and wife
and have some sort of
normalcy in our lives.
We're just gonna let time take its course
and hopefully we will recover one day
and rebuild our lives as a family.
(light music)
- Many people have argued to me
that all these wrongful convictions
and ultimate exonerations prove
is that the system corrects itself.
And if you take any time
to study this issue at all,
this phenomenon, you'll see that
that's just a ridiculous statement.
Look at what we had to do in this case.
We had to fight tooth
and nail for everything.
They refused to admit that
a mistake had been made
and we had to keep going and doing more.
This was the system fighting
back and trying to stop us.
And all the other cases we're litigating
across the state of Ohio right now,
all we're doing is seeking
to get the DNA evidence.
And then you have to get the court,
or the prosecutor, to
agree to let you test it,
and most of the time they
won't let you do that.
And then if they still
refuse to let you out
after you prove you're innocent,
you have to be lucky enough
to have someone like Earl
Mann, the true killer,
move into your pod with you
and drop a cigarette butt
in front of you so you can pick it up.
So it's not the system
correcting itself at all,
it's the system doing everything it can
to stop this sort of thing,
and then when it does happen
and we do break through
all the barriers, saying,
oh, this is an aberration,
it doesn't happen very often
and this just proves the
system corrects itself.
That's a ridiculous statement.
(light music)
(background chattering)
- Well, after Clarence was
released on December 15, 2005,
we expected a quick
indictment of Earl Mann.
That didn't come, so for
the last year and a half,
as I understand it, the prosecution
has been investigating this case.
And today, which is July 11th,
they are going to formally
charge him, arraign him today.
I brought a picture of my
mom, and today is for her.
I don't know what my
reaction is going to be.
I know that yesterday it felt like
today was going to be Christmas,
and today I'm a little
nervous, a little angry.
I don't know what my reaction's gonna be,
but I am happy that it's finally
come to fruition on this.
I just can't wait until
they formally charge him.
It's just gonna be a big
amount of pressure off of me,
because this is for my mom and
I vowed to do that for her,
and here we are today.
(background chattering)
Seeing him in the courtroom was difficult,
but I felt good about it.
But I have a lot of confidence
that things are gonna go
the way they should this time.
- [Woman] You're gonna follow
this thing all the way through?
- All the way through, I'll be here
every time that he's in that courtroom.
- [Woman] I see you're
moving on with your life.
- Yes, this is my fiance, Patrick.
Clarence and I are divorced now
and he is in a relationship
and I'm engaged.
And we're just tryin' to pick up
the pieces again and live life.
A lot of misconception that
the public and the media have
is that I wasn't doing this
for the sake of my marriage,
I was doing it because it
was the right thing to do.
I couldn't stand the thought
of him sitting in prison
for something he didn't do.
The vow that I made to my
mom was the main objective.
And just the feelings of husband and wife
were somehow buried
underneath all the pain
and devastation that I went through.
- Yes, it was a shock, it was
definitely one of the issues
I had to deal with in my life
since I've been home for
a year and a half or so.
But with the help of family
and friends, I'm managing,
I'm managing and trying to get forward,
move forward with my life.
- [Narrator] Earl Mann
is left to contemplate
a capital murder trial and
possible death sentence.
He decides it's in his best
interest to plead guilty.
- Hey, I need some hairspray,
does anybody got any?
Today he is supposed to plead
guilty to aggravated murder,
attempted aggravated murder,
and guilty to the rapes
on both my mom and my niece.
We gotta go.
Oh, I'm just nerves,
nerves, nerves, nerves.
- [April] Yeah, I'm startin' to get em.
- I feel like I'm walking into a coliseum
where I have to fight the lions.
I first and foremost did not
wanna put my niece through another trial.
She's been very riddled by fear,
and I think that just putting
her through that again,
and the whole entire family,
would just be too much,
too much for what he's worth.
So we decided that the
guilty plea was satisfactory.
He'll be in court, which
is terrifying to Brooke.
She's been just a nervous wreck.
And muster up that strength.
I want, in the courtroom when we talk,
I want people to remember
what happened to my mom.
And this day, we can finally feel
that she's at rest in peace.
(gavel pounding)
- [Woman] All rise.
This court of common
peace is now in session.
Your Honorable Judge Robert
M Gibbons is now presiding.
- [Woman] Thank you, Your Honor.
This is case number 2007062079,
State of Ohio versus Earl Mann.
- Judge, at this time Mr.
Mann is prepared to withdrawal
his former plea of not
guilty, entering a guilty plea
to the counts as outlined
by the State of Ohio.
- Do you understand your rights
and the effect of the guilty plea?
How do you plead in the charge
of first aggravated murder?
- Guilty.
- Further understand your rights
and the effect of the guilty plea,
how do you plead to the
charge of attempted battery
and murder as set forth in count three?
- Guilty.
- [Woman] Your Honor, there are a number
of members of the victim's
family that would like to speak.
- You murdered my mother.
(sobbing)
You beat her, you strangled
her, you broke her neck.
And then you raped her.
And then you tried to do
it to a six year old child.
You're a coward, you're a
murderer and you're a liar.
I hope you are locked away
for the rest of your life
like the animal that you are,
and you live in a cage
for the rest of your life.
And I hope you keep it
in the back of your mind
that you will never, ever again
walk a free man on this Earth.
Because you know why?
I gotcha, I found out what you were about
and that's why we're here today.
(sobbing)
- I think you are such a coward.
I was only six years old,
what could I have done to you?
What can my grandma have done to you?
And I'm sparing your life, I shouldn't be.
You deserve the death penalty.
I don't think you deserve one more breath.
- I was glad to be able to see him
and I knew I was gonna be
able to stand in front of him
and talk to him, and I knew
he was gonna recall himself
and flash back to Mansfield
Institution, the prison.
And I knew it was gonna hurt him.
- Mann, you and I have nothing
but courteous exchanges,
and I don't mean that to change today.
But it falls to me as the judge
to express this community's
utter outrage at you.
There seems to be a
depth of depravity in you
that is beyond understanding.
The poet Dante once spoke about hell
as being frozen ice as its lowest depths.
And Mr. Mann, I can only
say I find that in you.
The exchanges I've had
with you and seeing you,
I can only conclude, however reluctantly,
because I hate to say this of anyone,
that you are not fit to be in society
with the rest of us and you will not be.
(audience applauding)
Please, please, please, please.
I'd ask that however you
may feel, please don't react
until this is all over and
you're out of the courtroom.
- I don't need an apology from him.
And if he did say he was
sorry, I wouldn't believe it.
I wasn't lookin' for that,
what I was lookin' for was for him
to be in those shackles
for the rest of his life.
That's what I got.
- I'm hoping in time, yes,
I'm hoping in time I will forgive him.
- [Woman] How do you remain so calm?
- Well, I learned that while incarcerated.
It's not gonna help me
to be angry and irate.
I learned that while incarcerated.
- [Woman] How do you feel
about him taking this plea agreement?
- I believe he got it to
avoid the death penalty.
There's no doubt in my
mind on that subject.
But I believe he will
get what's coming to him.
And hopefully, he will come
to terms with God Almighty,
and before it's too late.
- It was just great to
see the final chapter
and the book finally come to a close,
and to see the family get that closure.
I guess one of the
messages I hope people take
is exactly opposite what
the judge said today.
The judge gave a speech about
how that it always fixes
itself and it took awhile,
but the wheels of justice
finally corrected themselves.
And I think this case
shows the exact opposite,
how many strokes of luck
have to happen in a row,
and coincidences to happen in a row
for someone to be able to do
what Melinda and Clarence did here.
And I think for the
vast majority of people
who are sittin' in their position,
all those cosmic
coincidences don't line up.
(light music)
- Well, Mom, this is it.
We all love you and we want
you to rest in peace now.
It's over.
(Melinda crying)
Oh, I do feel like there
is a lot of emotions.
Generally I rollercoaster
when somethin' big
like this happens, but this is phenomenal
and I feel very happy.
We finally have created the moment
where we can all say it's over now,
he's pleaded guilty and
we'll never forget my mother.
Always, always keep her in
our thoughts and our memories.
And I feel that she knows
and it's a big relief
that she can rest in peace now.
Dear Lord, thank you for this day.
It's been a day mixed
with so many emotions
and we thank you that
you brought us this far,
with all the people,
friends and family involved,
to bring down the man
who created this chaos.
And Lord, give us the strength to go on
and live our lives, and
let us help others, amen.
- [All] Amen.
(exhaling deeply)
(light music)
(background chattering)
- Oh yeah, I'm working
on reading a good book
that caught my eye, and
what I've read thus far,
it's pretty much my story.
And it's sad, but it's
true, and it happens, so.
I see a lot of myself in that book.
I think at times that
people just don't understand
what we as wrongfully incarcerated
individuals go through.
I think it's a man thing, or a guy thing,
that we think we can handle it on our own
and get through it and tough it out,
but I found out that that doesn't work.
(metal clipping)
Hopefully myself and the other victims
may have some sort of comfort out of this,
that the person that did commit this crime
was brought to justice
and held accountable.
So, yeah, the sun came out
and it's gonna be a good day.
♪ I dreamed I met you at a magic show ♪
♪ Saved a seat for me by you ♪
♪ A crowd of people turned
and watched the show ♪
♪ They split a lady right in two ♪
♪ Which side are you on ♪
♪ The dusk or the dawn ♪
♪ Midnight or noon ♪
♪ You're leavin' too soon ♪